Something different ...
有點不一樣....
Something like that.
像這樣。
How is foul?
犯規怎麼吹?
Foul is like that.
犯規聽起來像這樣。
- One extended.
一個長音。
What other whistles are there?
還有什麼其他的哨音?
At the end of the match..
結束比賽時...
Oh, I know, gentle whistle?
我知道，柔音?
Wait a minute...
等一下.....
THE WHISTLE
You are a supervisor, aren't you?
你是監督，對嗎?
There is some broken glass over there.
那邊有一些破掉的玻璃。
Glass?
玻璃?
There is a broken glass in the puddle.
水坑裡有破掉的玻璃。
Girls, are you playing?
女孩，你們在做什麼?
This is a place for footballers,
you can't sit here.
這是給足球選手的地方，你們不能坐在這。
Offside!
越位!
Number four is not on the offside position!
四號沒有越位!!
Fuck!
操!!
Number four is not on the offside position!
四號沒有越位!!
Look at the situation.
看一下狀況。
What the fuck, you idiot!
他馬的，你白癡嗎。
Hand.
手。
Go on!
繼續!
Offside, fuck!
越位阿，操!!
You aren't a referee, get it?
你又不是裁判。
What?
什麼?
Out.
出界。
No!
不!
It was out, but you put it on!
出界，
Fuck!
操!
You are silly!
你是白癡！
Are you talking to me?
你在對我說?
What was it man?
到底怎樣?
Ok!
好了!
He has attacked me at the back.
他從後面攻擊我。
So what, I've just whistled the foul
and you don't like that,
又怎樣，我吹犯規你並不接受。
I don't have to give him a yellow card.
我沒必要舉黃牌。
Where's the referee?
裁判在哪裡?
Mr. Manager!
經理先生!
I'm getting fucking crazy!
我他媽的快瘋了!
What now Mr. Referee?
現在怎樣，裁判先生?
Where is Mr. Manager of the club?
俱樂部的經理在哪?
Referee, they aren't fighting on a stadium,
it's not your business, let's play.
裁判，他們並沒有在運動場打架，和你沒關係，我們繼續。
But, there is a player over there, fighting.
但是有個選手在那邊打架。
I'm giving you yellow card
for leaving the stadium without permission!
我給你黃牌因為你未經允許就離開運動場。
Do you know what would have happend
if I hadn't gone there?
你知道假如我沒過去會發生什麼事嗎?
Are you hurt?
你受傷了?
No.
不。
Referee, please take notes that the fans
are beating the players, what's going on!
裁判，快寫下粉絲正在毆打球員，發生了什麼事!
But what can I do now?
但我現在能做什麼?
Close the stadium,
what a fucking crazy situation!
關閉運動場，這狀況真的是太誇張了!
There's no reason to beat the players!
沒有理由要毆打球員啊!
Ok, I'm taking notes.
我記下來了。
Fuck, the man will go to work
with a crashed face tomorrow!
操，那人明天會帶著張衰臉去上班!
He sometimes drinks my coffee.
他有時會喝我的咖啡。
When it's hot, yeah?
還熱的時候?
I came back once and there was no coffee.
我回頭看的時候咖啡已經沒了。
I cought him red-handed once,
我有一次當場抓到他，
he was standing on a chair
and drinking coffee.
他正站在椅子上喝咖啡。
Yes, Macieslaw?
是吧，Macieslaw?
They make me crazy on TV,
I watched elemination to Eurovision on TV,
我在Eurovision頻道看淘汰賽，
our representatives sang in English,
我們的代表唱英文歌很多年了，
for so many years
there was no Poland on a map,
都沒有波蘭，
People learnt Polish under death pressure,
人們在死亡壓力下學波蘭語，
so many people died, they fought
for independent Poland, against communists,
很多人死了，為了波蘭的獨立，對抗共產黨，
and now our singers sing in English,
only two words in Polish.
結果現在我們的歌手唱著英文，只有兩個字是波蘭文。
Because English is an international language.
因為英語是國際語言。
Sure ...,
當然.....
You will see ...,
你會看到.....
soon if you don't know English
in your own country, you will be useless.
將來在你的國家若你不懂英文，你就沒用。
“The Poles are not geese,
they have their own language”, ...simple?
“波蘭人不是鵝，他們有自己的語言”....了嗎?
And do you know who said that?
你知道這是誰說的嗎?
Kochanowski ...
Kochanowski(人名) ...
Very good?
對嗎?
Not really ...
錯了....
Who?
誰?
Rej.
Rej(Mikolaj Rej 波蘭文學之父 1505-1569)
Yeah ... maybe ...
恩....也許....
And for whom you are making the bouquet?
這花是要給誰的?
You know .., a woman has ordered it ...
就....一個女子的訂單....
She wanted with "Astromeria" ...,
她想要有小百合....，
you like it?
喜歡嗎?
Yeah ..., ok.
恩....還不錯。
Would you give such to a girl?
Or you would prefer roses?
你會把這花給女生?還是你比較喜歡玫瑰?
Usually girls want roses.
通常女生想要玫瑰。
It depends what girl ...
這要看女生.....
Yes, but 90 percent would prefer roses ...
是啊，但是九成的都會選玫瑰....
Once it happened to me
that a girl prefered daisies.
真的有一次，一個女生選了雛菊。
So, you first ask a girl
what flower she wants and then you buy it?
所以你問一個女生哪種花她喜歡，然後你就買那個?
No, come on …, on the first date
you don’t give flowers.
不，不是這樣....，
你不能在第一次約會時就送花。
Be careful.
小心。
Come up to the ball!
追上球!!
Go on, go on Zbyszek, go on!
繼續，繼續 Zbyszek，繼續!
Go on ...
繼續....
The guy fouled the guy in the penalty area!
那個人犯規了，他在罰球區!
No foul!
沒犯規!
What the fuck?
搞什麼?
Fuck, where was the ball?
操，球在哪?
It's a disaster, fuck!
太慘了，操!
Are you a fucking idiot?
你他媽的是白癡嗎?
Easy ... , easy!
放輕鬆....放輕鬆!
Give me your number?
你幾號?
Turn around man!
轉過去!
Have I told you that if everything is ok,
I will have new job only for a week yet.
我有跟你說過，假如順利的話，我在一個星期就會有工作了。
Why?
為什麼?
Because to 95 percent I have a new one.
因為95%我會有個新的。
Where?
在哪?
- In Polint.
- What company is it?
- 在Polint
- 哪間公司?
They do some plastic things, some parts.
他們做一些塑膠零件。
You must develop yourself,
你一定要提升自己。
you must look for a job which, apart
from money, brings you some satisfaction,
你一定要找個除了得到錢，還能獲得一些成就感的工作，
and not like that, improve your qualifications.
而不是像這樣，提升你自己的資格。
You have quite good education ...;
你有著不錯的教育...
do you want to be a worker all your life?
你想要一輩子當工人?
Or think about a private company.
或是去間私人的公司。
My business started
when I bought 52 encyclopedias,
我的生意在我買了52套百科全書時就開始了，
so far I have sold fucking three ...
到目前為止我賣了他馬的三套....
But I will sell them and earn on it.
但我會靠這樣來賺錢。
There was a good offer,
so I bought 52 pieces
他們的價格很不錯，所以我買了52套
and I still have got 45 to sell.
還有45套等著去賣。
For you I've got a special price
because I normally sell for 9 euros.
通常我一套賣9歐元，你的話我可以給你特價。
I was going to put it on the internet
but nobody wanted to buy it,
我本來想把它放到網路去賣，可是沒人想買。
so I decided to sell it personally.
所以我打算一套一套賣。
They've been fouling
and you haven't given any card.
他們一直在犯規，可是你都沒吹哨。
There was no card before
so you shouldn't give it now, only caution.
之前就沒吹過，所以現在也不會吹哨，提高你的警覺。
There was a caution before!
之前有過警告!
When was it?
什麼時候的事?
Ok, player number 11.
夠了，11號。
For what?
什麼理由?
For kicking the ball after I stopped the action.
在我叫停之後還繼續踢球。
Hey, referee!
嘿，裁判!
Fuck, foul!
操，犯規!
Will you get up or not?
你到底要不要起來?
I need some help.
我需要些幫忙。
I will help you.
我幫你。
Do you want some help from your team?
你需要你的隊友幫你嗎?
Come!
過來!
Handball.
手碰球。
No hand!
沒用手!
Hey, what's going on!
嘿，怎麼了!
Continue!
繼續!
Why are you surprised at the highest league,
你為什麼對聯盟最高級感到驚訝，
when they are fixing the match here, fuck!
當他們在這踢球時，操!
Idiots!
笨蛋!
Are you fucking mad?
你瘋了嗎?
Player number 17!
17號球員!
What?
什麼?
What? I should show you a yellow card!
什麼?我應該給你黃牌!
Bravo, well-done!
太好了，幹的好!
What the fuck is the referee doing?
裁判到底在做啥?
Fucked!
操!
He should have shown a red card, fuck!
他應該亮紅牌的，操!
It seems to me that I did it right.
There was a hand.
看起來我是對的，真的有碰球。
Fuck ...
操...
And the situation with the hand,
關於那個手碰球的事件，
maybe I shouldn't have shown him
a yellow card,
也許我不應該亮他黃牌，
but he was lying on the grass
and the ball was rolling towards him
但球正往他那邊過去時他正躺在地上，
and I think, he stopped it with his hand
when he was getting up.
所以我判斷在他起身的時候用手將球停住。
So you think it was wrong.
If there was no hand ...
也許你錯了。
假如根本就沒碰到手....
But it was!
就是有啊!
This is a kind of "Ruber",
這是種"Ruber"，
and this is "Aurera" ..., also "Pecherznica",
還有這是"Aurera"....,，還有"Pecherznica"
but you trim it.
這要修剪。
Nice, isn't it?
It is very good just for urban conditions.
很棒，不是嗎?
就種在城市的狀況而言算是很不錯的。
And you know, with such claims that
I would have fixed the score,
你知道，有傳言我有對比數動手腳。，
and you know, they treat me like a person
who came, took the money and went away,
你並不知道，他們將我視為來拿了錢就走，
as if I would have everything in my ass.
一點都不把我當專業。
They think that a referee has no feelings at all,
他們覺得裁判一點感覺都沒有，
and that he doesn't care about what he's doing,
一點都不在乎他在做什麼，
a referee is a fucking machine or a robot,
that he comes, gives yellow cards,
一個裁判就像是一台可惡的機械，或一個機器人，
他過來，亮黃牌，
and that the most important thing for them is taking
the money and then leaving, fuck!
對他們來說最重要的就是過來拿了錢就走，操!
And where is his psyche?
Where is everything?
他的心在哪裡?
全部的東西都在哪裡?
And listen ..., on the eleventh, you know,
there is the independence day, yeah?
在11號，就是獨立紀念日，
Independence day, it's your name's day.
獨立紀念日，你名字的那天。
Victoria will come over.
Victoria 會過來。
That's right, Victoria means victory,
沒錯，Victoria 代表著 victory(勝利)
finally she will defeat you.
他最後會擊敗你。
- Yeah, but is she a pretty girl?
- Beautiful ..., like you.
- 是啊，但她是正妹?
- 漂亮啊.....像你一樣。
What are you talking about?
你到底在說什麼?
- Pretty ...
- Pretty, yeah?
- 漂亮...
- 漂亮，嗯?
Foul!
犯規!
Player number 14!
14號
I have seen it!
我看到了!
And for you the same yellow card,
because you don't have to swear.
同一張黃牌，因為你沒必要說髒話。
I know that it is a scandal.
How you behave is a scandal.
我聽過這個傳聞，聽過你行為上的傳聞。
I'm only telling you that you can't stay
in the lowest football league,
我只是告訴你，你不能一直停留在最低等的足球聯盟，
you must constantly improve your skills.
你必須要不斷的提升你的技術。
And that's all, so far.
就這樣。
Summing up, I'm estimating you well.
總歸一句，我覺得你很不錯。
"How long in Wawel's castle
Zygmunt's bell sounds,
so long Marcin's Vistula river
will send a water to the see.
Our land will be standing,
stand up a royal town,
Wisła Kraków will win
because it's Marcin's club".
So Macius, are we resting?
Macius, 我們在休息?
After dinner? Are you full, Macius?
晚餐之後?你有飽嗎，Macius?
In a second, I have to go to a match, Maciek.
我等等就要去場比賽了，Maciek。
I will be running, and it will be raining,
我會跑來跑去~還會下雨，
and you will be lying on your bed and relaxing.
然後你會躺在我的床上休息。
You are lucky, Maciek.
你真幸運，Maciek。
And I have to contend with everybody on that pitch.
而我必須和球場上的每個人周旋。
Written and directed by
GRZEGORZ ZARICZNY